<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on Shorts</title><link>https://raivivek.in/</link><description>Recent content in Home on Shorts</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://raivivek.in/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>List of books I have read</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2019/list-of-books-i-have-read/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2019/list-of-books-i-have-read/</guid><description>Books are magic.</description></item><item><title>Physics of Life 2017</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2017/06/physics-of-life-2017/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2017/06/physics-of-life-2017/</guid><description>Frans Johansson, in his popular bestseller book The Medici Effect, makes an argument:
The intersection is the best place to innovate. These innovations change the world in leaps along new directions by opening up new fields, creating new information and allowing creators to become leaders.</description></item><item><title>Vim for Writing</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/09/vim-for-writing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/09/vim-for-writing/</guid><description>I happen to be a Vim user—not because I practice terminal voodoo or intend to push the limits of keyboard efficiency—because Vim is what I started with and had no reasons to move on.</description></item><item><title>Overview of BOSC and ISMB, 2016</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/09/overview-of-bosc-and-ismb-2016/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/09/overview-of-bosc-and-ismb-2016/</guid><description>This year I attended the Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology (ISMB) from July 8-12 in Orlando, Florida. But before I talk about my experience of the conference (and amazing Disney World!</description></item><item><title>A Letter in the Name of Science</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/08/a-letter-in-the-name-of-science/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/08/a-letter-in-the-name-of-science/</guid><description>Posted below is an email that I rediscovered in my mailbox a few days ago. I had no memory of it whatsoever, perhaps because I never received a reply from the intended recipient.</description></item><item><title>Open {data, science, source} - OpenSNP.org</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/08/open-data-science-source-opensnp.org/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/08/open-data-science-source-opensnp.org/</guid><description>April, 2016 “What’s the worst that can happen? Not like it will be different this time. some sleep”, I told myself as I prepared to brace the bad news. The clock moves closer to midnight with every passing moment, but I am too tired to think about it anymore.</description></item><item><title>Quick Data Plotting in R - II</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/05/quick-data-plotting-in-r-ii/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/05/quick-data-plotting-in-r-ii/</guid><description>In the first part of the posts on R, I outlined a couple of useful strategies for quick exploratory data analysis and visualization using R programming language. In this post, I will share a few more examples (in a case-study like manner) along with relevant plots for better demonstration.</description></item><item><title>Quick Data Plotting in R - I</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/05/quick-data-plotting-in-r-i/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/05/quick-data-plotting-in-r-i/</guid><description>Python is my all time favorite programming language. I use it all the time. It is simple, readable and easy to get started, something which I picked up four years ago when I went through the first offering of Interactive Programming with Python course on Coursera.</description></item><item><title>WIGI – an inspire grantee</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/05/wigi-an-inspire-grantee/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/05/wigi-an-inspire-grantee/</guid><description>The Wikipedia Indicators of Gender Inequality (WIGI) project aims to study and characterize gender representation on Wikipedia by studying trends in growth of biography articles. The project is led by Maximilian Klein, a PhD student at the University of Minnesota, and Dr.</description></item><item><title>Review: The Inner Game of Tennis</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/review-the-inner-game-of-tennis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/review-the-inner-game-of-tennis/</guid><description>In the book ‘The Inner Game of Tennis’, author Timothy Gallway talks about different aspects of learning (or acquiring) a new skill. He argues that key to acquiring any new skill requires contribution from two distinct entities in your brain, which he calls Self-1 and Self-2.</description></item><item><title>Writing My Journal of *TILs*</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/03/writing-my-journal-of-tils/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/03/writing-my-journal-of-tils/</guid><description>Have you ever wondered about your daily Niagara of words? ‘Language in Thought and Action’ by S.I. Hayakawa.
From the moment you wake up in the morning till the moment you go to bed, you are exposed to constant sources of information.</description></item><item><title>Metabolic Network Analysis - I</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/03/metabolic-network-analysis-i/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/03/metabolic-network-analysis-i/</guid><description>In this short tutorial, we will explore the basic steps of a metabolic network analysis.
For our convenience, we will avoid using full models or discuss their reconstruction methods, instead focus on simple reactions to create a theoretical background.</description></item><item><title>Review: Burmese Days</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/review-burmese-days/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/review-burmese-days/</guid><description>It is one of the tragedies of the half-educated that they develop late, when they are already committed to some wrong way of life. George Orwell, Burmese Days Burmese Days by George Orwell My rating: 4 of 5 stars</description></item><item><title>How to Give a Good Talk</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/02/how-to-give-a-good-talk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/02/how-to-give-a-good-talk/</guid><description>There are many more ways to get a presentation wrong than there are to get it right. Good presentors (and presentations) are hard to come by. But I believe it is a skill that can be learned and acquired.</description></item><item><title>WikiProject article submission</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/wikiproject-article-submission/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/wikiproject-article-submission/</guid><description>Almost an year ago, I had written a blog post about different Wikipedia WikiProjects and how one could contribute to them. In short, A WikiProject is simply an organized effort by the community of editors on the Wikipedia, where they try to curate and improve the quality of articles belonging to a particular genre or of specific interest to a group.</description></item><item><title>Notes from Systems Biology Winter School</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/notes-from-systems-biology-winter-school/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/notes-from-systems-biology-winter-school/</guid><description>This winter, I attended the fourth session of Winter School on Quantitative Systems Biology at International Centre for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS), Bangalore. The school is organized by the ICTS, Bangalore and ICTP, Italy in jointly as a part of their ICTP-ICTS Programme in Biology since 2012.</description></item><item><title>Notes from WMCB 2016</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/notes-from-wmcb-2016/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/notes-from-wmcb-2016/</guid><description>This weekend (Jan 9 - Jan 10), I participated in a workshop on mathematical and computational biology (WMCB-2016) organized at Indian Institute of Science Education and Research Kolkata (IISER-K). This annual workshop is co-sponsored by NNMCB, a group of multiple premier institutions in India that coordinate activities in the area of interest.</description></item><item><title>Lessons for Good Life</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/12/lessons-for-good-life/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/12/lessons-for-good-life/</guid><description>Robert Waldinger1, a psychiatrist at Harvard Medical School talks about a famous long term study of adult development done by Harvard and shares his findings about what made the lives of the participants happy or sad as they aged.</description></item><item><title>A challenging course catalog</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/09/a-challenging-course-catalog/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/09/a-challenging-course-catalog/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m very excited to talk about my course catalog for the fall semester, specially because it&amp;rsquo;s turning about to be pretty challenging and full of new information.
Prologue: During my research internship at Indian Institute of Science, I had the opportunity to attend several lecture series by eminent professors, who introduced us to different fields (e.</description></item><item><title>Bypassing Proxy Servers</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/09/bypassing-proxy-servers/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/09/bypassing-proxy-servers/</guid><description>IIT Kharagpur uses a proxy server to enable outside internet connections. Whatever be the use case from the perspective of the institution, it is a nightmare to use for us students.</description></item><item><title>Protein Knots&amp;colon; A tangled story</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/08/protein-knotscolon-a-tangled-story/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/08/protein-knotscolon-a-tangled-story/</guid><description>Journal Club is a weekly paper presentation session organized in our department by us, where one could present an remarkable research finding, discuss a new experimental technique or simply introduce everyone to a new or less explored field in the area of biology.</description></item><item><title>Working with pore forming toxin - II</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/07/working-with-pore-forming-toxin-ii/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/07/working-with-pore-forming-toxin-ii/</guid><description>Give a man a fish and you feed him for a day. Teach a man to fish and you feed him for a lifetime. Chinese Proverb This chinese proverb accurately describes my summer experience at the Indian Institute of Science this year.</description></item><item><title>Working with pore forming toxin - I</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/05/working-with-pore-forming-toxin-i/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/05/working-with-pore-forming-toxin-i/</guid><description>A learning experience is one of those things that says, “You know that thing you just did? Don&amp;rsquo;t do that.”
Douglas Adams, The Salmon of Doubt
Douglas Adam was correct about Experience.</description></item><item><title>research needs funding</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/research-needs-funding/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/research-needs-funding/</guid><description>Brian Farley writes ..
I&amp;rsquo;ve said this before on Quora, and I&amp;rsquo;m probably going to say it many more times, but, all of the problems in academia can be traced back to scarce funding and the ridiculous competition it engenders.</description></item><item><title>Papers per week</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/papers-per-week/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/papers-per-week/</guid><description>Research is to see what everybody else has seen, and to think what nobody else has thought. Albert Szent-Gyorgyi Reading research papers, literature survey as one may call it, is one of the primary tasks of any research enthusiast, student, academician, or researcher.</description></item><item><title>The Importance of Reading</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/the-importance-of-reading/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/the-importance-of-reading/</guid><description>As he read, I fell in love the way you fall asleep: slowly, and then all at once. John Green, The Fault in Our Stars Reading is one of the fundamental habits that we learn as a child.</description></item><item><title>Review: What is Life?</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/review-what-is-life/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/review-what-is-life/</guid><description>If a man never contradicts himself, the reason must be that he virtually never says anything at all. Erwin Schrödinger Written by Erwin Schrödinger, an eminent physicist and Nobel Prize winner, the book What is Life?</description></item><item><title>Diving Deeper into BLAST - III</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2014/11/diving-deeper-into-blast-iii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2014/11/diving-deeper-into-blast-iii/</guid><description>BLAST+ is an incredible tool and does it job in a pretty decent way. However, anyone who has worked with it for some time with some non trivial details has their own horror stories to tell.</description></item><item><title>Diving Deeper into BLAST - II</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2014/08/diving-deeper-into-blast-ii/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2014/08/diving-deeper-into-blast-ii/</guid><description>This is a follow up of the previous post where I was trying to parse the BLAST+ XML output to create an efficient data layer in SequenceServer. A critical and often demanded feature for the application was the ability to have a graphical overview of all the obtained hits.</description></item><item><title>Diving Deeper into BLAST - I</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2014/07/diving-deeper-into-blast-i/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2014/07/diving-deeper-into-blast-i/</guid><description>In my previous post, I mentioned about a project I was trying to work on: SequenceServer. Also, in the end I said that I would be writing about the BLAST algorithm (which is the backbone of this project) and how does it works so efficiently in producing alignments even with very long sequences.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Sequenceserver</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2014/05/introduction-to-sequenceserver/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2014/05/introduction-to-sequenceserver/</guid><description>Contributing to open source is quite an exciting journey. I embarked upon this path recently with few contributions to SequenceServer - A BLAST tool, a bioinformatics software built around BLAST+ that lets you setup a custom BLAST+ server to perform BLAST queries with your own database locally through a web interface.</description></item></channel></rss>