<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Vivek Rai (genes)</title><link>https://vivekiitkgp.github.io/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2014 16:11:04 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Easy BLAST tool - SequenceServer</title><link>https://vivekiitkgp.github.io/blog/easy-blast-tool-sequenceserver.html</link><dc:creator>Vivek Rai</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Contributing to open source is quite an exciting journey. I embarked upon this
mission recently with few contributions to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sequenceserver.com/"&gt;SequenceServer - A BLAST tool&lt;/a&gt;, which lets you set up custom BLAST+ server to perform BLAST queries with your
own database locally through a web interface. For those who are not familiar
with &lt;strong&gt;BLAST&lt;/strong&gt; or Basic Local Search Alignment Tool &lt;a class="citation-reference" href="https://vivekiitkgp.github.io/blog/easy-blast-tool-sequenceserver.html#paper" id="id1"&gt;[paper]&lt;/a&gt; - it is an algorithm which allows
quick comparison of biological sequence information which are long strings consisting
of amino acids (in case of proteins) or nucleotides (in case of nucleic acids).
It is exceedingly used by biologists all over the world to study newer
organisms, discovery of genes and finding similarity between proteins and so
on. One can see a working instance of the tool at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://antgenomes.org/blast"&gt;Ant Genomes&lt;/a&gt; website, maintained by one of the developers
and Professor at Queen Mary University London, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sbcs.qmul.ac.uk/staff/yannickwurm.html"&gt;Yannick Wurm&lt;/a&gt;. He's also the overseerer of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The program has already completed its major part of development and its stable version
is readily available for use. However, there were many &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/yannickwurm/sequenceserver/issues"&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; or feature requests
that were pending and can be worked upon. I got in touch with the maintainers and submitted
three pull requests for small few bugs and a feature. It was not a big task but I was
quite motivated with this small experience of working with the community, engaging with
the developers and obviously working with git. Also, since the tool is written in Ruby, I
had to spend some time brushing up the concepts of Ruby and understanding the code structure,
and methodologies followed for the development. Ruby is a concise and appealing language which is not very tough to
understand once you are in with the flow. Anyway, I plan to continue my contribution to sequenceserver
for quite some time and also encourage you to take a look if you are even just a little bit of
Biology enthusiast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will talk more about BLAST algorithm in general in my next post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils citation" frame="void" id="paper" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://vivekiitkgp.github.io/blog/easy-blast-tool-sequenceserver.html#id1"&gt;[paper]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.blastalgorithm.com/"&gt;http://www.blastalgorithm.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>alignment</category><category>biology</category><category>blast</category><category>genes</category><category>sequenceserver</category><guid>https://vivekiitkgp.github.io/blog/easy-blast-tool-sequenceserver.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 11:20:16 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>