<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Vivek Rai (resources)</title><link>https://vivekiitkgp.github.io/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 23:48:35 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Curated List Of Biology Resources</title><link>https://vivekiitkgp.github.io/blog/curated-list-of-biology-resources.html</link><dc:creator>Vivek Rai</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;It always has been a dreaded task for me to study during the examinations. For
those who may not be aware of my college's curriculum, may note
that we have a mid-semester and an end-semester evaluation exams; one during
September and the other in November. However, I appreciate the idea of a more
integrated and continuous evaluation schemes where the progress of students and
their understanding is continuously being monitored through small, concept based
tests, quizzes or other discussions than few life changing exams.
Moreover, these require one to divert all their attention exclusively towards
the exams, and it's preparation thereby hampering all the other engagements of a
student. Regardless, I won't discuss the pros and cons of such a system because
I have a more interesting thing to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now while preparing from one of my subjects (&lt;em&gt;Genetics&lt;/em&gt;), I noticed that the
information about different educational resources in Biology (or Biotechnology)
is very much fragmented unlike Computer Science. The knowledge about
established textbooks, popular research papers, and other resources is not
readily available, and one often has to go through a larger number of searches,
forums, and blogs to find some information worth reading. It's not surprising
to see different papers which review, collect and organize other tools and
resources, getting accepted into prestigious Journals. This effort is enough to
show the need to organize the vast amount of content out there in public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I came upon &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/josephmisiti/awesome-machine-learning"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; repository on GitHub, which curates a list of
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;awesome-machine-learning&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; frameworks, libraries and software (by language).
This project itself was inspired from another project called &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;awesome-php&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This motivated me to attempt a similar collection of biological resources with
the help of online community. I don't know if it'd be the best place to
end ones' search, but it'd be one of the best places to start with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repository is available at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/vivekiitkgp/awesome-biology"&gt;vivekiitkgp/awesome-biology&lt;/a&gt;.  Feel free to send in your
suggestions by creating a pull request, opening an issue or dropping me an
email (please do). This desperately needs more and more contributers for
ensuring visibility, and quality content. Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>awesome-biology</category><category>books</category><category>github</category><category>resources</category><guid>https://vivekiitkgp.github.io/blog/curated-list-of-biology-resources.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2014 20:09:40 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>