<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Science on Shorts</title><link>https://raivivek.in/science/</link><description>Recent content in Science on Shorts</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://raivivek.in/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Physics of Life 2017</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2017/06/physics-of-life-2017/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2017/06/physics-of-life-2017/</guid><description>Frans Johansson, in his popular bestseller book The Medici Effect, makes an argument:
The intersection is the best place to innovate. These innovations change the world in leaps along new directions by opening up new fields, creating new information and allowing creators to become leaders.</description></item><item><title>Overview of BOSC and ISMB, 2016</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/09/overview-of-bosc-and-ismb-2016/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/09/overview-of-bosc-and-ismb-2016/</guid><description>This year I attended the Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology (ISMB) from July 8-12 in Orlando, Florida. But before I talk about my experience of the conference (and amazing Disney World!</description></item><item><title>A Letter in the Name of Science</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/08/a-letter-in-the-name-of-science/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/08/a-letter-in-the-name-of-science/</guid><description>Posted below is an email that I rediscovered in my mailbox a few days ago. I had no memory of it whatsoever, perhaps because I never received a reply from the intended recipient.</description></item><item><title>Metabolic Network Analysis - I</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/03/metabolic-network-analysis-i/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/03/metabolic-network-analysis-i/</guid><description>In this short tutorial, we will explore the basic steps of a metabolic network analysis.
For our convenience, we will avoid using full models or discuss their reconstruction methods, instead focus on simple reactions to create a theoretical background.</description></item><item><title>WikiProject article submission</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/wikiproject-article-submission/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/wikiproject-article-submission/</guid><description>Almost an year ago, I had written a blog post about different Wikipedia WikiProjects and how one could contribute to them. In short, A WikiProject is simply an organized effort by the community of editors on the Wikipedia, where they try to curate and improve the quality of articles belonging to a particular genre or of specific interest to a group.</description></item><item><title>Notes from Systems Biology Winter School</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/notes-from-systems-biology-winter-school/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/notes-from-systems-biology-winter-school/</guid><description>This winter, I attended the fourth session of Winter School on Quantitative Systems Biology at International Centre for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS), Bangalore. The school is organized by the ICTS, Bangalore and ICTP, Italy in jointly as a part of their ICTP-ICTS Programme in Biology since 2012.</description></item><item><title>Notes from WMCB 2016</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/notes-from-wmcb-2016/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/01/notes-from-wmcb-2016/</guid><description>This weekend (Jan 9 - Jan 10), I participated in a workshop on mathematical and computational biology (WMCB-2016) organized at Indian Institute of Science Education and Research Kolkata (IISER-K). This annual workshop is co-sponsored by NNMCB, a group of multiple premier institutions in India that coordinate activities in the area of interest.</description></item><item><title>A challenging course catalog</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/09/a-challenging-course-catalog/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/09/a-challenging-course-catalog/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m very excited to talk about my course catalog for the fall semester, specially because it&amp;rsquo;s turning about to be pretty challenging and full of new information.
Prologue: During my research internship at Indian Institute of Science, I had the opportunity to attend several lecture series by eminent professors, who introduced us to different fields (e.</description></item><item><title>Protein Knots&amp;colon; A tangled story</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/08/protein-knotscolon-a-tangled-story/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/08/protein-knotscolon-a-tangled-story/</guid><description>Journal Club is a weekly paper presentation session organized in our department by us, where one could present an remarkable research finding, discuss a new experimental technique or simply introduce everyone to a new or less explored field in the area of biology.</description></item><item><title>Working with pore forming toxin - II</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/07/working-with-pore-forming-toxin-ii/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/07/working-with-pore-forming-toxin-ii/</guid><description>Give a man a fish and you feed him for a day. Teach a man to fish and you feed him for a lifetime. Chinese Proverb This chinese proverb accurately describes my summer experience at the Indian Institute of Science this year.</description></item><item><title>Working with pore forming toxin - I</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/05/working-with-pore-forming-toxin-i/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/05/working-with-pore-forming-toxin-i/</guid><description>A learning experience is one of those things that says, “You know that thing you just did? Don&amp;rsquo;t do that.”
Douglas Adams, The Salmon of Doubt
Douglas Adam was correct about Experience.</description></item><item><title>research needs funding</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/research-needs-funding/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/research-needs-funding/</guid><description>Brian Farley writes ..
I&amp;rsquo;ve said this before on Quora, and I&amp;rsquo;m probably going to say it many more times, but, all of the problems in academia can be traced back to scarce funding and the ridiculous competition it engenders.</description></item><item><title>Papers per week</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/papers-per-week/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/papers-per-week/</guid><description>Research is to see what everybody else has seen, and to think what nobody else has thought. Albert Szent-Gyorgyi Reading research papers, literature survey as one may call it, is one of the primary tasks of any research enthusiast, student, academician, or researcher.</description></item></channel></rss>