<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Letters on Shorts</title><link>https://raivivek.in/scribbles/</link><description>Recent content in Letters on Shorts</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 01:03:49 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raivivek.in/scribbles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Writing My Journal of *TILs*</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/03/writing-my-journal-of-tils/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/03/writing-my-journal-of-tils/</guid><description>&lt;p>Have you ever wondered about your daily &lt;em>Niagara of words&lt;/em>?
&lt;span>
 &lt;label for="sidenote-0" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number">&lt;/label>
 &lt;input type="checkbox" id="sidenote-0" class="margin-toggle"/>
 &lt;span class="sidenote">‘Language in Thought and Action’ by &lt;em>S.I. Hayakawa&lt;/em>.&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From the moment you wake up in the morning till the moment you go to bed, you
are exposed to constant sources of information. Whether it’s your morning
newspaper, your boss, a group of friends that you hang out with, or the
multitude of feed applications on your smartphone; your brain is being flooded
by a Niagara of words.
&lt;span>
 &lt;label for="sidenote-1" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number">&lt;/label>
 &lt;input type="checkbox" id="sidenote-1" class="margin-toggle"/>
 &lt;span class="sidenote">&amp;ldquo;[&amp;hellip;] by 2015, the sum of media asked for and delivered to consumers on
mobile devices and to their homes would take more than 15 hours a day to see
or hear. That volume is equal to 6.9 million-million gigabytes of
information, or a daily consumption of nine DVDs worth of data per person per
day.&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href="http://www.marshall.usc.edu/faculty/centers/ctm/research/how-much-media">&lt;em>How Much Media? 2015, Report on American Consumers&lt;/em>&lt;/a>&amp;quot;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>

Each of these sources has the power to shape
your thoughts and inevitably your actions by carefully
&lt;strike>manipulating&lt;/strike> controlling the nature, time and placement of the
content. Like it or not, every day you draw new inferences from things you hear
about people you may or may not know and create subtle judgments in your mind.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to Give a Good Talk</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2016/02/how-to-give-a-good-talk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2016/02/how-to-give-a-good-talk/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are many more ways to get a presentation wrong than there are to get it
right. Good presentors (and presentations) are hard to come by. But I believe
it is a skill that can be learned and acquired.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lessons for Good Life</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/12/lessons-for-good-life/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/12/lessons-for-good-life/</guid><description>&lt;p>Robert Waldinger&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, a psychiatrist at Harvard Medical School talks about a famous
long term study of adult development done by Harvard and shares his findings
about what made the lives of the participants happy or sad as they aged. While
the talk itself isn&amp;rsquo;t very detailed and offers a &lt;em>too long, didn&amp;rsquo;t read&lt;/em> summary, the
publications page&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> on the website offers a comprehensive and has an interesting list of
findings.


&lt;span>
 &lt;label for="marginnote-0" class="margin-toggle">&amp;#8853;&lt;/label>
 &lt;input type="checkbox" id="marginnote-0" class="margin-toggle"/>
 &lt;span class="marginnote">
 
 &lt;a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/robert_waldinger_what_makes_a_good_life_lessons_from_the_longest_study_on_happiness/transcript?language=en">Robert Waldinger: What makes a good life? Lessons from the longest study on
happiness&lt;/a>
 &lt;/span>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Importance of Reading</title><link>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/the-importance-of-reading/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raivivek.in/2015/04/the-importance-of-reading/</guid><description>&lt;div class="epigraph">
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>
As he read, I fell in love the way you fall asleep: slowly, and then all at once.
&lt;/p>
&lt;footer>
John Green,
&lt;cite>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11870085-the-fault-in-our-stars">The Fault in Our Stars&lt;/a>&lt;/cite>
&lt;/footer>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Reading is one of the fundamental habits that we learn as a child. Even
before our temporal abilities are decently developed (usually by the end of
third month after birth), people sing songs, lullabies, read stories or make
interesting noises to stimulate our brain. Not much later, reading becomes
out favorite activity where we have already irritated our parents to read
&lt;em>Winnie-the-Pooh&lt;/em> over and again for umpteenth time. This habit, however,
grows only up to the teenage years and then starts to diminish, only to
increase again later in
life.&lt;a href="http://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED496343.pdf">1&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>